Guide to the Robert Engelmore Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Robert Engelmore papers
1976-1998
1978-1986
SC0967
Engelmore, Robert
2.5 Linear feet
Collection includes documents regarding the computer programs/projects CRYSALIS and SACON; conference papers; copies of overhead slides for talks; and files pertaining to the computer company Teknowledge, Inc. Teknowledge files include stock papers, annual reports, correspondence, company publications and brochures; correspondents include Bruce Buchanan, Edward A. Feigenbaum, Rick Hayes-Roth, and Lee Hecht.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Robert Engelmore earned three degrees in physics from Carnegie Mellon University: BS 1956, MS 1958, and PhD 1962. He came to Stanford University in 1970 as research associate in the Heuristic Programming Project, Dept. of Computer Science, becoming Executive Director in 1985. He retired from Stanford in 1998. Engelmore was also a Program Manager for research in AI at DARPA, 1979-81, and a co-founder and director of Knowledge Systems Development, Teknowledge Inc., 1982-85. He died in 2003.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes documents regarding the computer programs/projects CRYSALIS and SACON; conference papers; copies of overhead slides for talks; and files pertaining to the computer company Teknowledge, Inc. Teknowledge files include stock papers, annual reports, correspondence, company publications and brochures; correspondents include Bruce Buchanan, Edward A. Feigenbaum, Rick Hayes-Roth, and Lee Hecht.
Access Terms
Buchanan, Bruce G.; Engelmore, Robert; Feigenbaum, Edward A.; Hayes-Roth, Frederick.; Hecht, Lee.; Teknowledge, Inc.; Expert systems (Computer science)
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Feigenbaum proposal (renewal): The Automation of Scientific Inference: Heuristic Computing Applied to Protein Crystallography; (duration May 1979-April 1981) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Williams and Nayak, “Model-based Autonomous Systems,” Fifteenth National Conference on AI, July 26, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Protein molecular structures (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CRYSALIS /Age – notes (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - CRYSALIS: Evaluation of design by Allan Terry and Engelmore; Memo HPP-78-12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CRYSALIS: paper for IJCAI, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - CRYSALIS ACA Conference, Boston, Aug. 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Protein crystallography tutorial, Jan. 15, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Presentation to Eamon Barrett (NSF) Sept. 5, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - CRYSALIS.doc [assorted papers] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Proposal: Automation of Scientific Inference (E. Feigenbaum) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - SKEL37 user’s guide (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fienup, J. R. papers 1978-79 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - “Interpolation Polynomials, Minimal Spanning Trees and Ridge-line Analysis in Density Map Interpretation” [abstract? review? of article by Carroll K. Johnson] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Skeletonization and beyond – outline (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - SACON: copy of 1978 report and miscellaneous items, 1977-84 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - SACON: final report notes 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - SACON: miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - SACON: IJCAI paper 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - SACON: historical 1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - SACON: old rule sets (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - SACON: A Knowledge-Based Consultant for Structural Analysis, report by Bennett, Creary, Engelmore and Melosh, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - “Knowledge-based modeling of physical devices,” talk by Engelmore in Italy, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pragmatics of knowledge system development: copies of overhead slides (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hamscher and Struss, Model-based Diagnosis (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - “Introduction to Artificial Intelligence and Knowledge-Based Systems,” copies of overhead slides from presentation to JAIMS, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “Introduction to Artificial Intelligence and Knowledge Engineering,” copies of overhead slides, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - “Basic Research in Knowledge-Based Systems,” copies of overhead slides from ISAI5 talk, ca. 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - “Knowledge Sharing Technology Project,” copies of overhead slides (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - KSL Overview, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Forum talk and assorted overhead slides (photocopies) 1991 and undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Summer ontology project, copies of overhead slides (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - “Automated Model Selection using Context-Dependent Behaviors”, copies of overhead slides (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - HPP Overview, copies of overhead slides, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - SunTechnology [issue on AI] Winter 1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - AI Applications in Natural Resource Management, Vol. 1, No. 1, Summer 1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - New Techniques in Structural Analysis by Computer, American society of Civil Engineers Preprint 3601, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Teknowledge: Business Plan (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Teknowledge: Business Plan (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Teknowledge: Reports (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Teknowledge: News and Stock Meeting (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Teknowledge: Founders/Consultants Committee (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Teknowledge: Advisory Board for Technology Strategy (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Teknowledg: phone directories (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lee Hecht, Seminar on Business Development, notes 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SRI email summer 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - SRI email Aug. 21-Oct. 20, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Teknowledge: - notes (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Car Charging Diagnosis and Repair Advisor 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Teknowledge: Briefing on Knowledge Engineering; Ford Aerospace and Communications Corporation (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Job objectives 1982-85 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Problem assessment questionnaire (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Teknowledge: WAVES User’s Guide (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - FURNACE Project 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Accountant: post-mortem re ADA (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - System Development phases (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Engelmore’s list of workshops in which he participated, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Retreat ideas, 1983-84 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Calendars 1981-82 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Teknowledge Inc. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Teknowledge- company brochures (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Teknowledge- business packet (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - AI readings (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Signal Understanding. Task Description and Statement of Work, July 1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Analysis of the Application of Knowledge System Engineering Technology to the Annual Planning Process. Prepared for the DOE, May 1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Teknowledge Patent Claims (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Teknowledge: miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Teknowledge: stock papers (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Teknowledge: stock papers (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Teknowledge: annual reports (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Teknowledge: merger and miscellany (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Teknowledge: Engelmore’s history (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Teknowledge: Application Screening Workshop (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Teknowledge: Fed. Sys. Consulting (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Teknowledge: Fed. Sys. Consulting (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Teknowledge: Fed. Sys. Consulting (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Beginnings of Teknowledge (1) 1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Beginnings of Teknowledge (2) 1981-82 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Beginnings of Teknowledge (3) 1981-82 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Beginnings of Teknowledge (4) 1981-82 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Beginnings of Teknowledge (5) 1981-82 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Teknowledge 1983-86 (1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Teknowledge 1983-86 (1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Teknowledge: notice of registration 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Teknowledge buttons (Box 5, Folder 11)